Welcome to the BugBash Podcast, where we talk about all things software correctness and reliability.
I'm your host, David Wynn.
Large language models can generate code in a flash, but that code is notoriously unreliable.
Traditional unit tests often can't put in enough guardrails to ensure correctness, even if they're written by the LLM itself, or maybe especially so.
This is where property-based testing becomes essential.
Today, we're joined by David MacIver, creator of the Property-Based Testing Library Hypothesis.
We discuss how to build robust feedback loops that are needed to make AI-generated code trustworthy.
We'll cover why standard AI coding benchmarks are flawed, how hypothesis makes property-based testing approachable, and the challenge of getting developers to think in invariance.
David also shares his perspective on the future of AI in software engineering.
If you want to build a reliability backstop for your code, vimed or otherwise, stick around.
Hey, everybody.
Welcome to another episode of the BugBash Podcast.
We have a very, very exciting and special guest with us today.
His name is David MacIver, and you have almost certainly used his stuff if you have done anything related to property-based testing.
David is the creator of Hypothesis, the most widely used library for PBT.
He has also done a lot of cool AI stuff at Anthropic, and he also knows a lot about test case minimization.
We're going to try and cover all those topics and others.
Welcome, David.
Thanks very much, Will.
I should say, it's actually David MacIver, not MacIver.
I'm so sorry.
That's okay.
We're here to catch bugs, and it's very kind to say I've done lots of cool stuff at Anthropic.
I did some cool stuff at Anthropic.
And you probably cannot tell us what it is.
I can tell you that I worked on LLM evaluations, among other things, and that's probably, and that's, I can tell you more interesting things I've done with LLMs after Anthropic, but that's where my interest in how they were evaluated got started.
So speaking of LLM evaluations, I have recently done a little bit of a deep dive into coding evals in particular that have been used with LLMs.
And we can talk later about why that was.
But I was a little bit horrified to discover that...
They're all terrible.
They're terrible.
They're so bad.
Yeah.
And even the benchmark, you know, Sweet Bench Verified, which has verified right there in the title.
It's like, you know, you made some change and like, did the unit test pass?
And I feel like the people on this podcast are well aware that just because the unit test passed does not mean that the software is in any way correct.
And I recently read another paper, which suggests that actually a very large number of like passing examples in these benchmarks do not actually work in any way.
What do you think?
So that's certainly what I...
I haven't like looked super in-depth at the quality of sort of the standard coding benchmarks in the last couple of years.
When I last looked at this, it was certainly the case that your standard coding benchmarks like human eval, they would regularly...
Well, in some of the cases, their gold standard example from the evaluation was also wrong.
But they would regularly accept things where, if you just added a couple more test cases, you would see that they were wrong.
There was a paper that came out a couple of years ago about human eval plus, which was essentially just doing the bare minimum to add a bunch more verification to the...
Human eval is also called codex often, I think.
It goes by a bunch of different names.
I can't remember why it goes by all these different names.
But it was for quite some time, like your sort of gold standard coding benchmark.
And when you just improve the quality of the testing in it, like all of the LLMs get a meaningfully worse result because they were quite regularly just giving things that failed, often on even interesting ways, often like your standard property-based testing, like if I pass an empty list here, it fails or like this fails if that number is zero.
But I think there were also more interesting failures as well, but I don't remember any of them.
I suppose it shouldn't surprise us that in interviewing our models, we recreated the same ridiculous process we used to interview humans.
I have used property-based testing in interviewing humans before, and it doesn't work very well.
That's right.
As to have a full property-based testing suite for evaluating coding tests.
I assume that if this is true of the benchmarks and the evals, it's probably...
I know you cannot comment on this, but I assume it's also true of the reinforcement learning process that's used to post-train these models for coding as well.
Yeah, thankfully, I don't know anything about that, which means I am allowed to comment on it.
I would imagine that at this point, people are probably doing better evaluations and post-training internally than the public benchmarks suggest.
I have no insider knowledge to edge about that one way or the other, so I'm speculating wildly.
But we've seen some really quite impressive improvements in maths and coding in like the last year or so, and I cannot imagine that we got those without them having some degree of better internal benchmarks that appear in the reinforcement learning, but I don't know what those are.
Yeah, interesting.
A thing that I have noticed is that coding agents tend to do very well at tasks that are like very local in the sense that like all of the code fits on a screen, or that the kinds of bugs that can be introduced are the bugs that you can notice by looking at like a screen.
And they tend to be quite bad at changes or at avoiding problems that involve the interaction of a bunch of disparate pieces of code.
And my initial guess as to this, and I think the conventional wisdom in the industry still, is that it's because like, it's because of the context window.
But I feel like as context windows have expanded and we've gotten better at stuffing more and more stuff into them, this is like not drastically improved.
And so now I'm starting to suspect that it's actually because, you know, because the kinds of tests that are being used to give these things RL feedback are maybe not great at catching issues that like, you know, connect multiple disparate parts of the software system.
Yeah.
So my understanding of the RL loop isn't great, but I think most training still happens on small context windows would be my guess, because it's like, or if not small context windows, like with things that would fit in a small context window, because I think it's so much more expensive to do good reinforcement learning on something that is like 100k or a million or whatever the current context window maximums are, I don't actually know.
So it's possible that some of those context windows.
But yeah, I think probably it's more in the training data, would be my guess.
But again, this is not something I have insider knowledge of.
I'm just speculating, but it does seem like, it's both easy to see why it would be easier to train models for one-shot tasks and then complicated interactions of things, because there's just like, it's much easier sort of straightforward reinforcement learning thing set up, right?
Like, here are your examples.
Do a thing.
Did you get it right?
I actually haven't spent a huge amount of time with the proper coding agent, and is the funny thing.
I use AI a fair bit in coding, but it tends to be sort of go to Claude or ChatGPT and say, hey, can you write me a thing?
And then I copy and paste the thing it wrote me into an editor, and then I inevitably do a bunch of work to make it actually work.
And it's still often super useful for doing things that either I don't particularly want to do or in an unfamiliar area.
I've definitely vibe coded web UIs, which I'm terrible at writing myself, and they sometimes even worked without me having to do a bunch of fixing.
Have you had success getting these agents to write property-based tests for you?
Like not the libraries, but the tests?
I've had medium success.
I think it's not something I've tried to do very recently, actually.
Because, you know, as I said, I tend to use these agents in circumstances where I don't know how to do the thing.
And so it's not necessarily, I've got some idea of how to write property-based tests after all.
So I don't tend to reach for them naturally when doing that.
When I've experimented with this in the past, what I found was with hypothesis in particular, they were pretty good at generating the right data.
And the tests they wrote were sort of boring and or slightly bad, but like not ridiculous.
Like there was a common problem in property-based testing, where people write property-based tests, which essentially like you recreate the application logic in the test, and assert that like the test version of the application logic do the same thing.
And that can be a super reasonable thing to do.
Like if you've got a hyper optimized for real version, and like a stupid simple version that you can write in the test.
And that's a perfectly reasonable test to write.
But often they would do this where there wasn't like any really meaningful difference between the code they wrote in the real thing and the code they wrote in the test.
But the generating data thing is interesting, because that is I think one of the things that users struggle the most with hypothesis.
Like I've tried to make it so that writing a test using hypothesis is just the same as writing a test not using hypothesis.
And that is sort of mostly successful.
But the how do you generate good data is not something that necessarily comes super intuitively to people.
And I think getting AI to do that part for them is probably like quite a good on-ramp to property-based testing, but.
So that's really interesting.
It's like you, you and Zach in maintaining hypothesis have had this real focus on user experience and making it understandable and easy to hold for people, which has clearly led to this steady growth in usage over time.
And it's really cool that that API is factored well enough that LLMs can help on-board new users for you.
Yeah.
Yeah, no, it's sort of...
I think one of the interesting things we've been seeing over the, like, the last year or two is that LLMs are real force multiplier on the thing that was good anyway, which is having documentation.
Hypothesis has both, like...
Like, it doesn't have an amazing documentation, but it has, like, a relatively comprehensible API.
It isn't documentation.
People write about it a lot.
There are lots of examples on GitHub.
And these are all of the things a human...
Oh, and also on Stack Overflow, I think.
These are all the things a human would use to try and understand it as well.
But there's...
But because they all went into the LLM training data, the LLM essentially, like, gets to distill a lot of that process a human would have used.
I've heard an interesting argument.
This is actually, in some ways, a bad thing because it creates a bit of a dampener on developing new tools.
Because essentially, it's, like, suppose someone invents Hypothesis++, like the next generation property-based testing, which is much easier to use than Hypothesis, then great, I would love them to do that.
Hypothesis definitely shouldn't be the last word in property-based testing.
But for quite some time, people will still prefer to use Hypothesis because Hypothesis is the one the LLM can tell them how to use.
And so, unless Hypothesis++ is easier to use than Hypothesis plus an LLM, then it will struggle to get traction.
So, can we, I think maybe we should take a step back here and talk a little bit about what property-based testing and Hypothesis are, and maybe why they might actually be about to go through a phase transition of importance in all of our lives.
And I want to set you up for this with a sort of provocative statement.
So, I basically think that LLMs are extraordinarily powerful tools, and they're also extraordinarily unreliable.
And the thing that allows you to turn something that's really powerful and unreliable into something really useful is being able to tell whether it's done the right thing.
And, you know, this is why generative models are so great for like image and video generation and for web UIs, because they're all things where you can kind of tell at a glance whether it did the right thing or not.
And if it did, great, you accept it.
And if it didn't, like you tell it to try again, and it tries again.
And you can just do that in the loop until it does the thing you want.
This is also why I'm actually pretty optimistic about using these things for like theoretical math, because we can actually mechanically check whether they have followed correct rules of inference.
But I think that software, much as we might like it to be otherwise, is something where it can be really hard to tell at a glance whether something is correct.
But I think possibly this other interest of yours, right, property-based testing and hypothesis in particular, like move the frontier on that.
So feel free to reject anything I just said or just give an intro of what you do.
But that's how I was going to set you up.
Yeah.
No, I think I agree with pretty much everything you just said.
I'm maybe fractionally less optimistic about the current state of the art of LLM's ability to take feedback, but we can get into that at an event.
So property-based testing, it's essentially testing where you get the computer to do some of the work for you is the way I've often framed it.
When you're writing a conventional test, you set up this very concrete scenario of like, here's some data, I do the thing with the data, here's what should have happened afterwards.
That's a bit of a parody, but that's roughly what a test looks like.
With a property-based test, you instead say for all data that looks like this, do the thing, and here's what should have happened.
So rather than running on a single concrete example that you provided, you give the computer the ability to specify the range of data.
And there are some sort of really easy examples of why this is valuable.
One is like, if you're doing some sort of like user log-in flow, you create a sort of a dummy user object and you test your flow, and you probably called it, said like Joe Smith, joe at example.com and so on.
And that all worked.
But like, what happens if Joe Smith is a mononym, or has like a complicated Unicode character in his name or like, what sort of email addresses do you actually accept?
And just having the library provide the user object rather than having this one that you don't otherwise care about, ends up testing a whole bunch of code paths that you might otherwise be neglecting.
In sort of an early workshop, I ran at a client, like someone commented that hypothesis would be worth it if it was only for its Unicode strategy, and I think that's probably right.
And you also can see this with dates and times, for example, like writing correct date and time handling code is brutal, and the hypothesis date, time, like a strategy, very carefully make sure it covers all the nasty cases that you really wish it wasn't going to ask you about.
I've forgotten many of the specifics, but the easiest examples of this are just like, have you got to be pierced right?
Floating point numbers are another one, of course.
Like the answer to, is your floating point code correct is probably not, but you can sort of specify bounds in it.
But beyond that, there's more complicated things.
So you can use hypothesis, for example, to generate sequences of interactions.
You can say, like, I've got this API, generate random API calls to it, and see if some sequence of them breaks any sort of crucial invariance, that kind of thing.
So it generally, like, opens up the ability to test a lot more than you manually would.
And you're still having to sort of write the test yourself, you understand.
It's not like a magic genie that says, find bugs in my code for me.
For that, you want antithesis, as I understand it.
But it's sort of like, it's a force multiplier again.
It's the amount of testing you do is probably like 10, 100, maybe if you're lucky, a thousand times as much testing as you would if you were writing out every single example by hand.
I mean, technically, it's 100 times in that it writes 100 times as many examples, 100, runs 100 times examples, but all as per test by default.
But the reality is that those 100 examples are probably not as good as 100 carefully handwritten examples, but they're certainly as good as 10 carefully handwritten examples.
I saw a study this morning actually, which was an empirical investigation of hypothesis.
They basically went and surveyed several 100 Python repos that used hypothesis.
They found that on average, a hypothesis generator was able to detect 50 times as many bugs as a unit test in any of these projects, which-
Wow.
Pretty nice headline stat.
Yeah.
Please send me a link afterwards, because that is frankly better than I would have expected.
Yeah, they basically introduced artificial bugs using mutation testing, and found which ones were found by what thing.
Fair enough.
But yeah, it's pretty sweet.
So now give us your take on how property-based testing makes the AI adoption story easier, if you agree with me on that.
Yeah, so I think this ties a bit into what we were saying about coding evaluations earlier, right?
If you look at the human eval slash codex evaluation, and simply adding property-based tests that assert that the LLM provided example is equal to the, provides the same answer as the gold standard or answer, which technically isn't a correct test for all of the human eval ones.
There's like one or two in there where there's some ambiguity, but this ends up just catching like a huge pile of cases where the LLM produces a superficially correct answer that is wrong.
So in general, like you can't really trust AI-generated code unless you've got some testing on it, and sometimes that testing is manual eyeballing it.
Like we talked about the, or you mentioned the video examples, we talked about the sort of the Web UI examples, and they're like some of our manual testing is probably fine.
But if you're getting the AI to write some non-trivial parts of your application, do you want tests to check whether it actually worked?
It usually didn't the first time, like and hot take if you're going to write tests, they probably should be good tests, and property is testing apparently catches 50 times as many bugs as normal testing.
So I guess that's the simple answer is that when you've got these AI agents that are rapidly turning out code, and you want a source of reliability, like using the ways we already know how to improve reliability seems like a no-brainer.
In your mind, does that mean that the human operator must write the property-based tests to clearly articulate their sense of the invariance?
Because what I see in practice tends to be that most engineers who are letting an LLM write large portions of their application are even happier to let the LLM write large portions of their test suite.
And so I have a fundamental question about what the tests are accomplishing at that.
I think that's okay.
At the very least, it's a self-consistency check on the LLM output.
The LLM has written the tests which indicates its beliefs about, like beliefs, scare quotes, about what the code is supposed to be doing.
And it's written the code, and actually running the tests does validate that it has at least a internally consistent fundamental model about what's going on.
I think you're going to end up with a lot of problems like the one I was mentioning earlier where it wrote the same code in the test and the application, so of course it worked.
And so I think, so it's not by any means perfect, but I would say that it is at least better than nobody writing the tests.
I think that the engineer should certainly read the tests and should sanity check them.
I'm morally confident that most people aren't doing that, but I think most of the people who aren't doing that probably weren't going to write working code themselves either.
So maybe that's too hard, I don't know.
But certainly, if they're not reading the test the AI wrote, then they probably weren't going to write the test themselves either.
Something I've noticed when trying to explain property-based testing to people is that there's a really big mindset shift from example-based testing to the idea of invariance that should always hold true.
And that a lot of developers have real trouble thinking about what the invariance of their code are.
And I think this is not like a fundamental problem.
I think this is really is like a familiarity thing.
Because if you ask leading questions, like hey, should the answer always be a positive number?
Hey, should the thing ever crash?
You know, like people know what their invariants are.
They just don't say what they are until they're prompted.
So I'm curious, first of all, whether you have personally experienced this as like a blocker to adoption of hypothesis.
And then I, or if you have some clever way around it, and then I'm secondly, I guess, curious whether you think LLMs could help with that problem at all.
For example, I don't know, maybe by reading your documentation and proposing some invariants for you.
So, as far as invariants go, I, there's a sort of original sin of property based testing, which is that it tries real hard to pretend that it's formal verification.
Like if, like the, I've forgotten the exact subtitle on the QuickCheck paper, but basically QuickCheck paper, QuickCheck claims to be lightweight formal verification.
It's not, it's a testing library.
You know, actually the Amazon guys call their property based testing lightweight formal methods.
That's right.
Yeah.
And, and I think that thinking in terms of invariance is sort of a downstream of this original sin, which is like, yes, okay, obviously what a property based test is, is it's asserting a universal property.
It's saying this thing must always be true.
But that's what most of your tests are claiming.
Like, they're, they're not obviously actually universal.
They're example based.
They're, they're a single thing.
But, but it's still in some sense, like if you look at it, if you look at a typical test name, the typical test name doesn't say, in this particular example, the thing should work.
It says when non-empty user should be allowed to, or, or something like that.
Like tests, tests are already expressing invariants, and what I've generally encouraged people to do is to, rather than worry about what are the abstract universal properties of my program, start from existing example-based tests and try to generalize them.
And essentially lean hard on the fact that people already know how to write tests.
And go from those tests to properties, rather than trying to learn an entirely new skill.
Yeah, that sounds really pragmatic.
So is, like, concretely the way this works is, like, you have an example-based test, you know, there's a constant three in it, and you try replacing the three with, like, you know, hypothesis dot, give me a random integer.
And then, you know, if you notice, there's also a three in the, like, thing we're checking, like, maybe we need to factor that into a variable and use the same number in both places or something.
Is that the example?
Exactly that sort of thing.
Or even more simply, sometimes you have constants and...
No, I guess not more simply.
Yeah, I was going to go back to the create a user object example, where you are creating user objects with constants that clearly don't matter.
And getting a hypothesis to provide those.
But yeah, but it is the same thing as your three example.
Yeah, I think Google may have actually pursued a very similar strategy recently.
So they have this Google unit testing library called Test, I think, which is widely used inside of Google, and I believe also has been open sourced as part of ABSL.
And I think, I think they basically wrote a like fuzzing like harness that's called fuzz test, which is just like exactly the same interface as like your way of defining unit tests, except that you can like annotate a parameter with just like, hey, give me whatever you want here.
And it just sort of all works exactly the same way.
And I think they found that by doing that, they were able to hugely increase adoption of fuzzing within Google.
Yeah, that makes a lot of sense.
And this is also why hypothesis is just designed to run as part of your normal unit tests.
Hypothesis is, well, historically it was designed to work with any testing framework.
But yeah, having something where you don't have to pick up a new way of running your tests, you don't have to do anything fundamentally different from your existing approach.
You can just sort of drop in a new library and start doing new things is, I think, super helpful for adoption.
I would assume that this Google library has some special support for generating a good range of protobuf-defined data structs.
And David, we've run into this interesting little hypothesis extension that works with open API schemas to generate fake data.
Is that an approach that seems promising to you?
Is this something that you guide people towards when you're doing these training workshops?
This is Hypothesis JSON schema, or something else?
I believe that's it, yeah.
Yeah.
Generally speaking, I think that it's worth writing your own generators if you can.
It's, one of the things I was relatively insistent on in Hypothesis with the typing support is that it's very easy to sort of gradually move away from it.
So you can have, like, if you've got a parameter to your test that has to be an integer, you can just say, strategies are from type integer.
I think these days there's even special syntax in the given decorator to do that.
I don't remember what it is.
I'll hand them.
But you need to make it so that it is easy for you to go, actually, I meant this to be a positive integer and replace it with an explicit generator which says, more strategies and hypothesis, which is a terrible name.
Hypothesis has a legacy of terrible names, and it's all my fault for not thinking about naming properly.
We have those two, early versions of the Antithesis API, referred like the literal ways of defining test properties, where you could call property.universal and property.existential to your point.
We thankfully changed those to always and sometimes.
Yeah.
It's definitely important to know when to change your names.
Hypothesis, they got a bit too entrenched.
And also in hypothesis, we never come up with a better name for strategy, partly because the obviously correct name is Generator, and that means something different in Python.
And the hypothesis name itself is just also problematic, but super entrenched.
But anyway, to continue on the point, like being able to gracefully bit by bit replace the bits the hypothesis has done for you, with bits where you have more manual control, without having to essentially go all in on one approach or the other is, I think, super useful.
And I very occasionally have found hypothesis JSON schema super useful, but it lacks this graduality property, where it's not easy to go from a hypothesis JSON schema generated thing to something more constrained.
I mean, you sort of can.
Hypothesis has this filter method which lets you apply an arbitrary predicate, but it's not recommended as the main way to control your data generation because it essentially has to do rejection sampling.
Try the thing repeatedly until you get a correct answer, which ends up with you throwing away an awful lot of data in some cases.
So I guess I don't want to be too negative about hypothesis JSON scheme.
I think it's a great thing.
I've often been very glad it exists, but it most of the time is not the thing I would reach for, particularly not when getting started with property-based testing.
I'd love to ask your take.
We've touched sort of on UX a few times here, and I would love to hear your bigger picture thoughts about developing a good and approachable UX for a very complicated and difficult system, because I find myself facing the same challenge right now.
I think you're one of the most successful people ever at doing that.
Your colleague Zach actually gave a whole talk about this at BugBash last year, and I think it was really good and really useful for me, but I would love to hear your thoughts too.
I think that how to do good UX is that there shouldn't be any cliffs.
It's essentially, like, it's okay if your thing is difficult to use, but every time you have, like, a really sharp jump in the difficulty level, you lose people.
And the first cliff that a lot of people have, or a lot of tools have, is on getting started.
And so, and that's going to be where you lose, like, almost all of your potential users, right?
And so, with hypothesis, the getting started story includes things like you absolutely can't have an external command runner that you have to use in order to use hypothesis.
It has to be integrated in your normal testing workflow.
You need to be able to generate all of the easy data you care about out of the box.
You need to be able to...
Those are probably the two big things.
I guess, like, having a good setting system where, like, if your tests take too long or if you're running into other problems, you can just configure the behavior as arguably a second one.
So that's, like, the getting started story.
And so anything that you can do that basically makes it trivial to get started is really, like, the most important possible UX thing.
But after that, it needs to be, like, every time they want to do something new, then that needs to be easy too.
Like, you can imagine a world in which I figured out the magic prompt that gives an LLM the ability, like, takes a project and produces a perfect set of hypothesis tests for it, right?
That's, I think, not the world we live in right now, but, like, it could be the world we live in in, like, three years' time, maybe less.
But then the user has to maintain those hypothesis-based tests, and if it's not easy for them to gradually evolve the existing code base, or to make change, or to say, actually, this parameter now needs this, add this constraint to this parameter, or make other changes to that, that is, like, that's a new cliff.
And it's not that they will go and delete those existing tests necessarily, but they're probably not going to, like, be enthused about keeping using hypothesis.
The other sort of big UX principle that I think drove hypothesis early on was essentially just, like, pay attention to what's annoying.
And this really ended up being the principle that defined a lot of the hypothesis API, because hypothesis has this internal shrinking thing going on, where for those who don't know, shrinking in property-based testing basically means that when it first finds a example or a test case that makes your test fail, it's probably going to be big and complicated and hard to read.
Shrinking is the process that sort of cuts out the unimportant bits and tries to turn it into a simple thing.
And hypothesis has a novel approach to shrinking that essentially means that you, the user, never need to even know this exists, with certain caveats of like, you do need to know it exists when it does badly, but it usually doesn't.
And classic property-based testing had two big problems with shrinking.
One was that it would often break like the invariance you sort of carefully set up in your test data.
You would say, this has to be a positive integer, and it would always generate a positive integer initially, but shrinking would sometimes go, okay, it's currently 100, but what if we tried replacing 100 with minus 1?
And so you would shrink from what was a real bug to a fake bug basically, because your initial test case was a valid example demonstrating a real problem, and your shrunk test case was a like something that just violated one of the preconditions, and so it doesn't matter.
Sorry, I'm not quite clear why would it sometimes do that?
Presumably, if you know what the preconditions are, you could avoid violating them in your shrinking process.
So there are, if you've explicitly set this as a precondition in the test, as well as in your generator, then the shrinker would say, ah, the precondition is being violated, so this is an invalid example.
But if you just said, generate me an integer from 1 to 100, say, then that isn't a precondition in the test.
It's an implicit precondition in the generated data.
See.
And in this example, it's easy to add a precondition.
Sometimes it is like harder to impossible.
Like the most dramatic example of this ever was when we, so I've successfully published like technically two, but really one academic paper about hypothesis and about how it shrinker worked.
And for that paper, we did a somewhat ridiculous flex of, there is a co-generator called Seasmith, where, which generates random C programs and has the guaranteed property that every program it generates is undefined behavior free.
And then these are these large complicated programs that you also want to do shrinking on.
And when you do this normally with, you use something called C reduce, which cannot check whether the C program is undefined behavior free, because in general, this is just like, I think in general, in general, this is impossible, but you can do a bunch of tooling that does conservative approximations.
So you need to run it under Valgrind and like compilers with WL flags and so on and so forth.
And so you can only do like a pretty good approximation to undefined behavior-free checker.
We just backed C Smith onto the hypothesis generator and got the hypothesis shrinker to run on it.
And so it just like happily shrunk C Smith generated programs and got the undefined behavior-free guarantee, well, for free.
Because every shrunk program was a C Smith generated program, so it satisfied all of its natural variable guarantees.
Oh, okay.
So your shrinker doesn't work by modifying the test input.
It works by calling the generator again and asking for simpler examples.
Yeah, exactly.
It manipulates the...
Effectively, what it's doing is the generator is calling some pseudo-random number generator, and initially, that is something that looks like a normal pseudo-random number generator.
And then during shrinking, it's something that hypothesis has thoroughly raked the dice and manipulates it in ways that causes the generated thing to be smaller.
Fascinating.
Yeah, so it never needs to touch the generated data, which is actually turns out to be a really important property in Python in a way that it wasn't in Ascult, because in Python, you can mutate data.
Does your shrinker try to do ablation analysis as well?
Will it just not invoke certain generators at all?
Or if you have a recursive set of generators, right?
I have generator A, which can call B or C.
During shrinking, will you just deactivate C maybe or B?
No, generally not.
From hypothesis' point of view, that's, or from the shrinkers point of view, that's fairly opaque.
When you've generated A, B, or C, all you know is, at the shrinker level, is that you requested an integer 0, 1, or 2.
This then sort of picked the next generator, and then you requested some more bytes.
It has a little bit more information than that, but not much.
Yeah, so it's interesting.
So it might just be something to do with our domain and our customers.
I think when it comes to fault-tolerance testing or distributed systems testing, ablation is very useful, because root-causing these bugs is often very, very hard.
And so, you know, being able to ask, is it possible to find the bug without fiddling with the clock?
Is it possible to find the bug without restarting a process?
Is it possible to find the bug without calling this API?
It's like actually super helpful from a diagnosis and root-cause point of view.
Yeah.
No, I think for, I think this is a case where hypothesis and antithesis just have quite different trade-offs.
I think hypothesis has a much sort of simpler class of structured examples than the sorts of things you're dealing with.
Like I think that in like the stateful testing, which is sort of what I was pointing out with the generating long sequences of API calls, that is a case where like some ablation might be helpful.
We don't do any, but like it might be helpful if we did.
But I think for the most part, it doesn't matter very much if you're generating like a relatively smallish structured test case for a specific test.
The other big advantage hypothesis has here is just like tests and hypothesis are super fast compared to antithesis.
Like a slow test and hypothesis is you took a couple of seconds to run a test case, while as I think in antithesis, that would be a blazingly fast test case.
So there are a lot of things that like in theory could be helpful, but probably don't matter very much under these sorts of performance characteristics.
Yeah, I think that one, you know, we, as with many companies, right?
We have like ambitions to world domination, but have started in like one particular place.
And I think that there's like, there's always ways in which the place where you start, like biases you and causes you to, you know, view the world in like an inaccurate way.
And I think one thing is just as you say, the systems we're testing are so big and so slow, that the like slowness of all of the rest of our system, it just doesn't really move the needle.
And so we haven't been under very much pressure to make it like blazing lightning fast.
And I think that if we someday started trying to like, you know, help the same users who today are using hypothesis to test their like Python data structures or simple Python programs, like this would immediately become a huge, huge, huge sticking point.
And like, one good example of it is, we don't really make much effort to make the first five seconds of the test the most valuable possible five seconds, and the next five seconds, the next most valuable five seconds, and so on, right?
Like, if you, if you're going to do a bunch of random stuff and generate a bunch of random cases, surely you should be like scoring your random cases some way, or like looking at whether they provoked bugs in the previous version of the software or something.
You have some idea of how, you know, where on the Explorer exploit trade-off this particular random case is, and you should clearly have a different bias towards different parts of that distribution over the course of your test, right?
And that's just like a thing we've never even thought, you know, we've never even started.
Yeah.
So, I think like the obvious bit to start to me is something that Hypothesis also did, which was, is just having a test database.
So, Hypothesis saves all previously seen failing test cases in both their original and shrunk forms, and uses those early on to just try those.
And just having a...
So, the original motivation for that was actually because Hypothesis is writing your development loop.
So, if you have a...
If you have like, you run your unit test and they fail, you want that when you rerun them, they fail exactly the same way and as fast.
But it's proved useful, like, above and beyond that, like it's...
And so, it's not just that for retrying a single thing, it's also like slippage occurred during test case reduction.
So, actually, you started with one bug and you moved to another, and you fixed the bug you moved to, but not the original one and things like that.
So, just like stuff you have previously seen to be useful is just like the lowest possible hanging fruit for early viable things.
Yeah, Google's internal fuzzing as a service has, I think, a really pragmatic compromise on this.
Basically, if you check in code into Google, which has a fuzzing target defined, it will just get fuzzed continuously with spare Borg cycles.
But if the fuzzing finds any crashing inputs, those get added to a seed corpus for your particular piece of software, and those then, it just runs through every such crasher pre-commit on every future time you try and commit code.
Which I think is like a nice way of balancing the pros and cons of exploration versus running things you know will crash.
And they have effectively open sourced that.
That is exactly how the Go fuzzing support works.
Yeah, I always found that as a user, the user experience of this end hypothesis is really nice because it just kind of completely eliminates the need for you to write regression tests.
Like, I found a bug because I was writing bad code in the way that I will probably write bad code again in the future.
And I don't need to specially take a moment to reify my idiocy in a handwritten example test just for free, and often slightly quietly so I don't need to point everyone else at it very explicitly.
Get this nice database entry that protects me from that class of bugs later on.
I do often end up adding them as explicit examples in the source code when I run into a bug that makes me go, oh, yeah, that's a good point.
I should probably check for that.
So Hypothesis does also let you, as lightweightly as possible, add them as regression tests built into the existing test as part of the source code.
That's a great thing.
That is really nice.
Yeah.
It's basically you add an at example decorator in the test.
It's these days, I think it will usually even suggest, like offer to create a git patch for you and says, would you like to apply this patch?
It's...
Whoa.
I keep running into bugs with the git patch feature that I haven't been able to track down, ironically.
So, I find that the automatic patching only works about 50% of the time for me.
And I keep meaning to sort of take a weekend and sort of dig into why that is.
But it's a great feature when it works and it's not hard to do it by hand, even when you don't get the automatic patch apply.
This is strikingly similar to your view on LLMs and reducers in general.
It only works 50% of the time, but you can tell when it's not working.
So 50% is still useful.
Yeah.
Yeah, no, absolutely.
Although this particular one I would like to work on to present to the time.
And I feel this is more achievable than LLMs.
That's fair.
It is a more tractable problem.
Yeah, I feel like our spin on the like, it's okay if it works a small percent of the time is, if you have a time machine, then a tactic that works 1% of the time, 5% of the time, I mean, it's incredibly valuable, right?
Like you just rewind and then you keep doing it until it works.
And that's sort of, I try to, I feel like that's a very useful intuition pump for why, you know, why techniques like fuzzing or like antithesis can, can do a better job of testing software than like a very, very smart RL agent, you know, without having, without being anywhere near as smart or as good at RL, right?
It's like an RL agent needs to have a policy that works 99.9999% of the time, because, you know, it needs to succeed a single run through the program.
I think there's something to be slightly careful of in all this talk about like what percentage of the time something works, which I think is sort of pointed at a little bit by your time traveling example, which like there's a really big difference between in 100% of cases, it works 90% of the time and in 90% of the cases, it works 100% of the time, right?
Yes.
Like, it's very easy to write software.
So, and I think LLMs are often an example of this.
Like an LLM, so you'll see in a lot of the LLM evaluations, these pass at K metrics, which is essentially if you give it K times to try, does it succeed?
Like, how often does it succeed at least once in those?
So like, pass at 5, for example, means if it tried 5 times, did it, were any of them successful?
And so what you will see is, say, an LLM has a rating of 80% on some benchmark in pass at 1, and if it was truly, like, independently 80% successful, then you would expect that, like, pass at 2 is, oh god, I can't do the mental arithmetic in my head, but it's going to be like 90%.
Like, the pass at K would converge to 100%.
But in reality, what happens is, like, the pass at K converges to 85%.
These are all made up numbers, by the way.
I'm not, like, citing a particular benchmark.
Because all of the unreliability is in the example, rather than in the LLM's response to the example.
Well, not all of the unreliability, but, like, there's sort of, like, two different metrics.
One is the fraction of test cases in which it's plausible that it works, and the other is the, like, reliability of it working on test cases that it works.
Um, and those leads to two different numbers, which you do need to make importantly different trade-offs around.
Yes.
We, so there's an interesting, we have an interesting version of this problem, which is, you know, Antithesis has many tactics that it can use to try to make your system do something cool.
And perhaps, let's imagine one of those tactics was completely ineffective, right?
It never did anything good.
Well, we're like, aha, we're very clever.
We've bounded the amount of energy that our fuzzer can spend using any given tactic to some fixed constant of the total exploration energy.
So if, if, say, I give each of my tactics one over n time in the fuzzer, then like at worst, they'll make me like that percent less efficient.
And so I've got bounded downside if I just add a random new tactic.
But it's actually not quite right.
Because a tactic could be, they can sort of destructively interfere, right?
Tactic could continuously drive the system under test into a state where it's really unfruitful to do anything, including with any of my other perfectly good tactics.
And so actually, this math doesn't quite work out unless you go to a lot more trouble.
Because there's all these other effects.
The same is true with like strategies of where to start exploration and so on.
So we had to actually get a lot more robust and detailed about, you know, we wanted to have a property that I could add a new experimental tactic or strategy to our fuzzer, and I would know that at worst, it would only make things a little bit worse.
But it turns out getting that property is quite hard.
Well, there's a concrete example here, so like people have some intuition for this.
Like if we're testing a database, simulating like a complete failure of a hard drive is very likely to drive this system into a state which is like, it's not working, but it's not working in an uninteresting way.
That's totally expected, and no further fuzzing is going to make it interesting.
Right.
That's not a bad example, yeah.
You know, if, right, if you're, maybe like the computer game example here is like, if you have a tactic that like is always making you die and go back to the start of the game, like that is going to destructively interfere with other things that could be making progress.
The sort of natural thing that I would think to try, which you can tell me whether this works or whether it doesn't, is rather than bounding the total amount of energy, like bounding the total number of runs that a tactic can be used in.
So essentially, like, each run turn off some of the tactics, so that a given tactic is turned on with only probability 1 over n per run, say.
Yep.
That's a good idea.
That's basically swarm testing, you know, which is a technique that we actually use quite a lot of.
One of my favorite papers, by the way, and we talked before once about how it's also in the papers.
Yeah, I guess for those who don't know, swarm testing is the idea that sometimes you can actually find more bugs in your system by turning off a subset of your tests.
And if that sounds crazy to you, you know, here is maybe a motivating example.
And it's a good motivating example because it literally happened to me once.
So imagine you're, this like literally happened.
You're designing a new cache data structure, right?
And there's like two operations you can do on your cache.
You can insert things and you can remove things, let's say.
And so you go and you get Hypothesis, which is a great tool for testing data structures.
And you're like, hey, I've got two generators.
You know, we can insert things, we can remove things.
Go to go to town.
And you know, gosh, I'm brilliant.
There's no bugs in my cache.
This is so cool.
I see where this is going.
Right.
The problem is, The Bug, which actually once caused an outage at Google, is in the garbage collection routine, which runs when the cache gets to a certain size.
But I'm exponentially unlikely to generate a very, very large run of insertions without any intervening deletions from my cache, unless I was very clever about that and thought about that.
And so what that means is that my test is actually not ever hitting this case.
But if some percentage of the time when I'm testing, I just turn off the deletion method, then I will hit this very easily.
And it turns out that that insight generalizes to all kinds of testing of all kinds of stuff.
It's really, really crazy how important this idea is, and how not well-known it is, given how important it is.
I was going to say, yeah, I'm also super proud of this paper.
Earlier versions of hypothesis actually implemented swarm testing by default.
That feature got lost with the a bunch of the changes to shrinking and serialization that happened in the 2.0 version of hypothesis.
Sorry, I think that was technically 3.0 version of hypothesis.
There was a very short window between 2.0 and 3.0 because I screwed something up.
And I've been meaning to put it back in for ages because it was a great feature.
I think this is another case where also the trade-offs of how much you're writing matter a lot because I think it is a better feature for long-running fuzzers than it is for short-running fuzzers like hypothesis.
This isn't a super well-validated theory in my part, but I think it's true.
Certainly, I have never had an example where I've gone, oh, I should really add swarm testing back in so that this example doesn't happen.
But I might not have noticed if I...
That makes a lot of sense.
I mean, this is like a...
I guess when I put my skeptical, busy industry programmer hat on, like, this is a very interesting theoretical resolve.
But like, regular tests suffer from the same problem.
Just like I wrote a lot of tests and they pass.
I just didn't write a test to cover the important thing.
And my sense is like we converge on solving that with test coverage.
There's some, like, you know, red line along the side of your code in the pull request, and it...
You got to make it bright red, which means that you've covered that chunk of code a bunch in the tests.
But I...
I rarely see things like this paired with property-based testing.
I...
Why not?
Like, why isn't property-based testing more closely married with coverage guidance?
So, in hypothesis, there's a reasonable amount of work on combining with coverage, actually.
Essentially, none of it that I can take credit for.
But you can plug a coverage-guided fuzzer in as the backend for hypothesis.
But by recollections, you're not allowed to use it on commercial software.
That might be true.
I think that is only for the hosted version.
I think that you can do it locally, but don't quote me on that.
Readers, you must read the license.
Yeah.
As I say, I can take very little credit for the coverage-guided fuzzing park.
That was mostly Zach's work.
I had always intended to add that as a feature, but never got around to it.
So I was very happy when he did it for me.
There's also, I'm afraid I'm blanking on the name, which is embarrassing.
Taiki, I want to say, which is some quite a great work other people have done on visualizing what property-based testing is doing that is sort of coverage-informed and does show you what lines are covered how often.
So there's some work there.
In terms of the general answer of why this is not as central a feature as it could be.
I think a lot of it is this short test run times thing again.
I think that most coverage-guided fuzzers, like there's a rule of thumb I have from a friend.
I think this was actually Alex Gross who wrote this one testing paper, but I may be a misremembering.
That essentially American fuzzy lobs starts being useful after its first 100,000 or so examples.
Because it's designed for fast tests and long-running fuzzing runs, that's fine.
But if property-based testing is running only in your CI and as part of your development workflow, then you don't get to run 100,000 examples.
You get to run 100 examples.
And how to use coverage in a way that is useful in your first 100 examples is, I think, something of an unsolved problem.
I think that makes sense.
I guess the thing that I was imagining was a little different.
Where example-based testing to its credit is very explicit and very clear.
And it's easy as a developer to have an intuition about the portions of your code that are being exercised by the example test you just wrote.
But part of the point of property-based testing is to shove a lot of that into a somewhat more opaque black box where you're ceding control for exactly what's happening.
And in the development loop, it feels like it would be nice to have some coverage guidance from some longer running process to inform me while I'm writing the test that I actually have not done a good job.
And it would be nice to know that upfront instead of two weeks later when I've gotten enough spare board cycles to find out that actually there's seven crashes that I would have found had I just thought a little harder or let a coverage guided thing tell me that I missed some important chunks of code.
Yeah.
I'm a big believer in 100% test coverage.
I guess my personal feeling is that the point at which this should have been caught is at the point of the pull request being opened and it showing you like, here's the code in your pull request that hasn't been covered by the tests.
I do often do what is absolutely a poor man's version of what you're asking for, which is at this point, I add a bunch of assert false statements into my code where the code hasn't been covered, crank the number of examples that hypothesis runs up to 100,000 or so and run it and see where it crashes.
If it doesn't crashes, then something's gone wrong, and I genuinely haven't covered that code.
If it does crash, great.
I've now got some explicit examples to add to the source code.
Well, that's covered.
That makes sense.
Now, this is a very janky workflow, and it would be much better if it did all this automatically for you, but at present, it doesn't do that.
Yeah, the antithesis answer to this is basically what we call sometimes assertions, which, you know, formerly known as existential assertions, basically an assertion that occasionally a given case is reached in the test campaign.
And the nice thing about that is it's not just asserting that a location was reached, but potentially that the combination of a location and a condition was reached, which, you know, I think my cynical answer to why most, you know, most property-based testing people don't think a ton about test coverage is that it's because they're a little bit too perfectionist.
And test coverage is a very, very lossy signal of how well your tests are covering your code.
You know, if you imagine trying to test a Python interpreter, if I achieve 100% coverage of that interpreter's lines, I have not begun to exercise that interpreter's behavior, you know, and I think maybe this true fact is like a little bit too present in the minds of some PBT enthusiasts and means that we throw the baby out with the bathwater.
But, you know, a sometimes assertion or an existential assertion does in fact let you get a little closer to that, to that real MI testing.
That's another example, by the way, where the trade-offs between antithesis and hypothesis are very different.
Like, hypothesis very explicitly doesn't support existential or sometimes assertions because 100 test cases is not enough to reliably trigger them.
And at that point, you've got flaky tests and flaky tests are the end of the world.
Like, it's really important for anything that's property-based testing shaped to own these stochastically fail, like in cases where there is a real bug.
And so it's obviously like you would like it to reliably fail, but if there are any bugs, but it's really important that it can only unreliably pass, it can't unreliably, like a fail is not a false signal.
And sometimes assertions on small numbers of task cases that you get to execute are just absolutely going to ruin that property.
Yep, that's super true.
Very briefly, sort of circling back to what we were talking about with LLMs and the sort of usefulness of property-based testing and antithesis and hypothesis for them.
I think that one of the big problems that we are with LLMs right now is that they are not very good at taking feedback.
So I think even with this— You're absolutely right.
Yes, okay, sometimes they're too good at taking feedback, but don't then incorporate it into their actions.
So I think right now what you get when you incorporate these stronger signals into a VibeCoding workflow or a stand-alone agent coding agent workflow is that you get an LLM that is essentially repeatedly beating its head against the better tests.
So one of the other things that I'm interested in at the moment, and I've been working with the GenLM group, who are a group of academics who work in constraining LLM behavior, is to try and do things that sort of boost LLM reliability, and to sort of do more constrained generation, and to try and generally improve that end of the workflow.
Because I think like right now, the way we're treating these LLMs is essentially like they're a magic oracle that can like you put in strings, you get out strings, and you don't have any other recourse to change their behavior than that, or than like changing the strings you put in.
And I think that is very much going to sort of limit us and in terms of like making them a reliable component of software engineering.
And I very much don't have all the answers there, but I just sort of want to sort of note that, like, we need to sort of work on both parts of the puzzle.
And like one part is how do you get them good enough feedback so that you can tell them when they're doing the wrong thing.
And but the other is like, how do you steer them to get them to do the right thing?
And I'm sort of really hopeful that we'll be figuring that out over the next couple of years, because I think if we just try to improve, like, general purpose software engineering on one end and training on the other end, I think at some point we're going to get stuck and it's going to be interesting to see when and where that happens.
Yeah, it is a little crazy if you think about it, that we have this incredible set of model weights, let's say.
And the first way that we figured out for extracting value from it, was like slapping a chat interface on it and instructing it to complete my sentence.
And it worked really well for some things, and so then we've just kind of gotten stuck with it.
When there's probably like many, many other ways of extracting value, that we haven't just like haven't really thought about.
Yeah.
Maybe not.
Maybe this is a really deep thing.
Where actually like software engineering as a discipline, like compared to many other fields of human endeavor, we have like really good objective functions for whether things are correct, or at least such objective functions are within our reach.
And maybe the answer is that if the tool is only 80% reliable and we want one-shot answers without like repeated loops through the agent, that these are like fundamentally best suited for chatty interfaces, where actually like the thing I want is a low effort answer, where I don't care that much about its quality.
Like I'm baking lemon cake and like anything that vaguely resembles a lemon cake recipe is like kind of fine.
I don't need like the French Culinary Institute version.
It's a very dismal take on the utility of our current endeavors, but it seems hard to overlook.
So I was going to say it's probably true that we're never going to get the best possible version out of our LLMs, right?
I think an LLM is in some sense a mediocrity engine, right?
Like, it'll give you a pretty good answer.
It will never give you a great answer.
And some of that I think is down to how we're training them and some of that is probably just intrinsic.
The reason I pause while saying that is I've actually had some very impressive conversations with GPT about mathematics recently.
Like, it's not been producing world-shattering new mathematical results, but it has been behaving as a more competent human mathematician than I would have expected.
Well, it's not a human mathematician, but it's been behaving equivalent to a more competent human mathematician than I would have expected.
So, but that's again a case where there's a really good objective function, right?
Is it also possible that the corpus of written mathematics is just like definitionally produced by the 0.1% of best mathematicians?
Like, versus the corpus of lemon cake recipes, which is like polluted by people who have no idea what they're doing.
Or the corpus of software, which is definitely going to get there.
Yeah.
No, it's true.
But I think it has to be a feedback thing as well, because I think that if you were to try to ask ChatGPT a year, two years ago to do mathematics, even like telling it to think through step by step in a way that is largely automated by think tokens these days, I think it would have produced garbage.
And by the way, although I say it's been very impressive, this isn't to say it hasn't been making stupid errors as well.
Like, it's just that it's been producing quite high quality results, which sometimes contain errors, which I have to call it on.
And oddly has been much better at taking corrections on its mathematics than it ever has been on the software.
Don't know why that is.
I had kind of a similar experience, actually.
I was recently trying to learn a new kind of math and a little bit of analytic number theory.
And basically, basically, there was a thing I was having real trouble understanding.
And I asked Claude to explain it to me.
And its explanation, like, it wasn't perfect.
Like it actually got a few things importantly wrong, which I was then able to call it on and be like, that doesn't make any sense, you know.
But it unstuck me, actually.
It actually, you know, it gave me like a really useful analogy to think about.
And it like helped me relate it to something else I already knew.
And I was like, wow, that was useful.
Yeah.
I sadly have to report that ChatGPT is currently better at mathematics than Claude is.
You should try.
At least in my experience.
Like I've tried talking to both of them about mathematics, and I've found Claude at best unreliably helpful was, like almost all of my mathematical experiences with ChatGPT have been good.
I'm sure that this is like by the time this podcast is live even, this may no longer be true.
Like this is one of those things where like everyone's leapfrogging everyone else all the time.
But like at the time of this recording, I much prefer ChatGPT for helping with mathematics than I do Claude.
Super interesting.
I think that kind of ties a neat bow on things, right?
Even in this final little conversation, good objective functions and good reinforcement learning can turn imperfect tools into increasingly good partners for humans.
And that can be true of LLMs as it is of tests.
Awesome.
Thank you.
Thank you so much for joining us, David.
Thank you very much for having me.
It's been a pleasure.
Thanks for listening to the last episode of the BugBash Podcast for 2025.
We'll be back next year with new voices, topics and more, all centered around software correctness and reliability.
If you've enjoyed the show, tell your friends.
And if you want to meet other like-minded people in person, consider attending the BugBash Conference, April 23rd and 24th in Washington, DC.
Find all the details at bugbash.antithesis.com.
We'll see you next year.